# **Paul Soares**

*Wilhoit Rd – Salem, Oregon Phone*: (971) 370.0724

*Email*: Paul.Soaresfz1@gmail.com

## Systems Management – Application Engineering – Systems Architecture Design

Results oriented professional with over 20 years of proven experience in the Information Technology industry as a Systems and Application Engineer, Technical Architect in the development of highly available and secure IT application and infrastructure architectures. Expert level design, analysis and issue management of fault tolerant, secure systems and network infrastructures. Development and management of ITIL process frameworks including Problem, Issue, Change, Release and Configuration Management. Experience across Finance, Medical, and Insurance, in the public and private sectors.

"Paul is very high level and would have no problem stepping in to most any technical role from engineering to management.

Projects were always done on time and at a very high caliber."

Betty Schanrock – Enterprise Engineering Manager, Franklin Templeton Investments

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Enterprise Application Engineer, Enterprise Application Engineering)— Advantech Consulting – 2017 - 2020
Lead Enterprise Solutions Engineer, Enterprise Engineering — Delta Dental Insurance Company — 2006-2017
Lead Security/Manageability Architect, Digital Health- Platform Development Capabilities, Intel Corp - 2005 - 2006
Technical Engineering Lead, Information Technology Group, Security National Servicing Corporation - 2002 -2005
Lead Security Engineer, MesoTech (Department of Defense), - 2001-2002
Enterprise Project Engineer, Franklin Templeton Investments, -2000- 2001
Technical Project Engineer, Sierra Nevada Hospital, -1998- 2000

### AREAS OF SPECIALTY – TECHNICAL COMPETENCIES

#### **EDUCATION & PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATIONS**

# **❖** SUMMARY OF EXPERIENCE – Enterprise Engineer – Enterprise Engineering

(Advantech Consulting)

- Microsoft Enterprise Systems
- Windows server engineering
- Expert troubleshooting and problem analysis
- IT support restructuring and planning
- Applications integration
- Database and network redesign
- Needs analysis
- Security analysis & audits
- Security Remediation and server hardening
- Network Sniffing and protocol analysis
- Planning and deployment
- Server and desktop deployment planning

# SUMMARY OF EXPERIENCE – Enterprise Solutions and Systems Engineer – Enterprise Systems and Projects

(Delta Dental Insurance Data Center)

- Technical Lead for Microsoft Enterprise Systems
- Technical Lead for Metavance Claims Processing system (Windows Server, Citrix, Oracle Tuxedo, VMWARE, 115 servers, 1800 users, UNIX backend)
- Technical Lead for Pitney Bowes Document Imaging system (Windows Server, VMWARE, 44 servers, 400 users)
- Technical Lead for Oracle Hyperion and Hyperion Strategic Finance systems (Windows Server, VMWARE, LINUX/Oracle DB, 12 Servers, 84 users/testers
- Technical Lead for Automation and Performance (Windows 2008/2012, 87 servers, VMWARE/HP Proliant blades, 40 testers)
- Network sniffing and protocol analysis
- Linux and Apache
- Cloud Computing Architectures
- Design and specifications
- Tier 3 problem management
- CITRIX Engineering
- MS Exchange, Azure, SQL, IIS, SCCM/SCOM, Sharepint
- Change Management
- Release Management
- Active Directory and LDAP
- Security Remediation and server hardening
- Tivoli Backup Solutions
- Disaster Recovery Planning and implementation

## **❖** SUMMARY OF EXPERIENCE – Architect – Security-Manageability

(Platform Development Capabilities, Intel Corp)

- Team leadership and project management
- Complete system architectures spanning the complete OSI model
- Analysis of policies and procedures and how they meet security requirements
- Analysis of manageability and security current practices
- Threat analysis of potential risks to health care platforms
- Analysis and design of platform security architectures
- Design of security processes for Platform Lifecycle (PLC)
- Defining implementation of the platform security strategy for platforms and products.

- Partnered with the product design teams within the Digital Health organization to implement the capabilities and technologies into fully functional and secure platforms which includes embedded controllers for medical instrumentation and treatment, to handhelds, mobile devices, desktops and/or workstations and servers for medical specific usage and others
- Partnered with architecture teams, cross-functional teams, engineering extended teams, to ensure that platforms meet overall requirements
- Regulatory compliance (HIPAA) in the areas of privacy and security

## **❖** SUMMARY OF EXPERIENCE – Lead – Technical Engineering – Information Tech

(Security National Servicing Corporation (SNSC))

- Design of secure architectures based on the .Net framework
- Design and rollout of pre-production windows 2000/2003 application server images
- Implementation and maintenance of Gramm-Leach-Bliley financial security compliance program
- Business Analysis of current program, policies and procedures and how they meet security requirements
- Design of secure architectures of ASP.NET and Web Services
- Design of system builds and administration
- Apple Technologies
- Analysis of potential risks to projects
- Architecture of policies governing lifecycle development and lifecycle security
- Architecture of database driven Risk Analysis program
- Design and Implementation of security processes into SDLC
- SDLC usability and restructuring
- Development of user training program
- Establishment of procedures for oversight
- Testing of key controls and procedures

## **❖ SUMMARY OF EXPERIENCE – Lead Security Engineer**

(MesoTech (Department of Defense))

Security lead in an application development effort for the Department of Defense.

Lead on multiple separate projects and processes

- Secure build design and deployment processes (IIS 5.5, SQL 2000, TS)
- Secure Software Development integration planning
- Quality assurance in testing of application security requirements
- Application and system requirements analysis
- Consultation and development of an administrators manual for the system
- Audited and engineered secure Windows 2000 server system prototype that was the master to be cloned and implemented at the Department of Defense.
- Consultation on server builds and application deployment strategies, thin client builds, and maintenance strategies.

## **❖ SUMMARY OF EXPERIENCE – Enterprise Project Engineer**

(Franklin Templeton Investments)

Project lead on multiple separate projects and processes, many which were multi-tier and required, development and planning with secure advanced technical solutions, and documentation.

- E-business development test lab
- NT/2000 Server Image design
- Security Analysis and design of test lab for e-business application development
- Integrate Document imaging database into Web front-end, (3 sites, server clustering, disaster recovery, application integration, and change management.
- SQL Database Administration and maintenance planning
- Titan Migration Project
- Security Analysis and design
- NT/2000 Server Image design
- Migrate titan application off of older technology, onto new secure servers

- Migrate SQL database
- Omni Source Project
- Requirements analysis
- Migrate Omni application server to new fault tolerant, secure scalable architecture
- Rules engine migration and planning
- Global Image Re-architecture
- Analysis and design of architecture
- Investment Document system redesign.
- Application integration planning.
- SQL Database engineering
- Test Planning
- Specifications and network analysis
- Extensity server application project
- Security Specifications
- NT/2000 Server Image design
- System analysis
- Architectural Design
- Implementation planning
- Network analysis

## **❖** SUMMARY OF EXPERIENCE – Enterprise Project Engineer

(Mercy Healthcare West)

- IT support restructuring and planning
- Applications integration planning
- Database and network redesign
- · Needs analysis
- Security analysis & audits
- Year 2000 planning and implementation
- Systems migration planning and implementation
- Training and mentoring staff